If you were born into the gentry in the
16th and 17th century, [music]
there's a good chance you'd be sent off
to Europe to learn how to be a
gentleman. It's in the name. But what
would you learn? I've come to London to
find out.
Right, guys?
Today I'll be following in the footsteps
of the young men on their grand tour of
Europe, an educational right of passage
in which the art of jeweling
and dancing were very much central to
the program.
How much time and dedication did it take
to learn the skills required not to
embarrass yourself and tarnish your
family name? If you're caught doing it
out of time, mega embarrassment.
[laughter]
>> Oh, that looked a bit awkward, didn't
it?
>> Don't fall flatly face.
>> And what was at stake if you didn't take
the assignment seriously enough?
>> Is it going to hurt
>> a little?
>> Sorry. That was almost in. I'm so sorry.
In the balls.
When you think of Brits abroad, you may
well picture boozy football fans causing
trouble and getting on the nerves of the
local population.
Well, back in the late 1500s, young
English lads were also traveling to the
continent, not for football matches or
to cause trouble, but to learn about
European culture, art, philosophy, and
religion in what became known as their
grand tour.
Starting their journey in France, the
men would acquire a coach from Calala
before riding onto Paris, their first
major stop.
From there, they would then head south
to Italy or Spain, carting all their
possessions and servants with them.
On the itinerary were lessons in
speaking European languages, discussing
art and literature, as well as more
practical activities.
But there was a darker side to being a
gentleman.
In Europe in the 15 and 1600s, it was
not uncommon for those of the
gentlemanly classes to challenge each
other in a fight to the death purely on
the basis of words and actions that
might offend each other's honor.
Jeweling was the secret ritual of a
class. And belonging to that class
depended on strict adherence to its
codes.
If I was to become a gentleman, I'd need
to learn about this code. To practice
for jewels, fencing was a vital part of
a young man's training on the continent.
But how quickly could an absolute rookie
pick up the basics? I had come to
Fighting Fit Fencing Academy in North
London to find out.
Fighting [music] Fit already has an
impressive alumni list, including
Catherine Beardmore, senior British
Championship title holder in 2017, as
well as active roster, namely
Catherine's younger sister Emily, who
was part of the GB fencing squad.
Like many of the men sent to Europe back
in the TUDA and Stewart era, I was being
thrown into the deep end. First step for
me was getting into some of the gear.
Before I was given any more equipment to
start training, I took the opportunity
to speak to lead coach Sebastian Palier
for a quick crash course in the history
of the sport.
>> Hi Seb. Um, I've got some of the gear
on. There'd be a little bit more than
this. Um, I'm interested in the art of
fencing itself in the 17th century. Is
that still very much to prepare people
for jewels or is it more of a sport?
>> Yeah, at that point it still would have
been to prepare people for jewels. So,
uh, a foil, specifically the weapon
you're going to be using today, would
have been used as a kind of training
weapon and then the EP, which is a kind
of slightly heavier version of this,
it's still a point weapon. So, you're
still hitting with the tip, would have
been what they would have actually used
in in the the jewels.
>> So, that's all part of being a
gentleman, you know, defending your
honor. You're going to have to go into a
jewel with them, and that's why they're
sending these people to to try and
practice. You mentioned uh epe and foil.
>> How has the art of fencing developed
from the 17th century to now? Obviously,
there's a few different versions of it.
>> Yeah. So, I mean, with the advent of the
modern Olympics, it's split into the
three different disciplines. So, we've
got foil, ep, and saber, and they're all
slightly different in their in their
rules. Um, the foil is uh a much thinner
blade, slightly lighter, and you can
only hit the torso, which is what you're
doing today. So, you've got the electric
jacket or the lame on there, which is a
scoring area. Um, the EP everywhere is
target and it's just whoever hits first
in EPA. So, it really simulates that
kind of jeweling of you just trying to
hit and not be hit,
>> right?
>> Um, and the Saber is more like a a
cutless or something like that. Is
designed as a cavalry weapon. So, in
saber, you'd still be wearing the
electric jacket and it's everywhere from
the waist up. So, as if you were on a
horse, you're not going to be aiming for
the for the other person's legs. You're
going to be aiming for the uh the upper
body and even the head as well.
>> Yeah. You mentioned the uh electric
jacket. When does that get introduced in
the period of fencing?
>> Yeah, so that was introduced kind of I
think around the 50s or 60s. I might be
wrong. Um it has changed a lot over the
years. Originally it was just like a
really simple box. You would be wearing
a wire and as soon as you hit a light
would come on. Now they're much more
sophisticated. They they've changed a
lot of the timing systems. So um now in
foil and saber for example, it's really
different. They share similar rules, but
in foil, you have much longer between
like me hitting you and you hitting me
for the box to show that we've both hit,
whereas in Saber, it's super super
tight. So, you would have to hit me
almost in instantaneously. And in EP,
it's even tighter. Um, so with with the
electric system, it's made it a lot
easier to to referee fencing and to
understand for people who are viewing as
well as uh who's scoring and who's not
scoring.
>> Is it going to hurt?
>> A little. Um, but most of the equipment
will will kind of deaden any feeling
that that you have. So,
>> okay. Not if my foot works good. So,
let's uh
>> Yeah, don't be hit and then you won't
get hurt.
>> Let's h crack on with some training
then.
>> Cool.
>> I was hoping my odds of not being hit
would be ever more increased by the fact
I was not actually facing anyone in my
onetoone lesson.
That was until a certain impostor
entered the gym.
Historian and Betwix the Sheets podcast
host Dr. Kate Listister was on her own
mission to make my grand tour as
difficult as possible. It seems we'd be
learning together before about to test
our skills.
>> Do I have to slap Luke with it first?
>> If you like
>> and challenge him to a jewel.
[laughter]
>> Okay. Right now we're kitted up. We're
ready to start fencing, but first we got
to learn how to fence. [music] So, if we
could just take a space on either of
those red lines at the back of these two
metal strips, that would be great. And
then just turn and face me. Okay. Right.
So, in fencing, we can only go forwards
and backwards. So, first thing we got to
set up our on guard position or your
ready position. So, just put your strong
foot forwards. Cool. That's it. And your
back foot just turns through 90° like to
make an L shape with your feet. That's
it. Now, just lift your arms up. Same
thing. You're kind of making an L shape.
So your sword arm is fac facing forwards
like directly at where your opponent
would be. Your back arm just comes up to
the side to help you balance. And last
and most important bit just bend your
knees. That's your on guard position.
Okay. Now to move forwards super easy.
Your front foot goes first and your back
foot catches up. So just take a few
steps forwards. Get comfortable. So it's
always front foot first, back foot
catches up. That's it. To go backwards
just the same. So it's just reversed.
Last thing we're going to learn in
footwork is just how to attack our
opponent. We do that with a fencing
lunge. So we break that into three bits.
So first bit is we start to move our arm
first. So you don't need to strain it
all the way, but just kind of aim at
where you want to hit. Make sure your
arm is moving forwards towards the
target. Then we make a small kick with
our front foot and just push with your
back leg. So you put all three together.
It's like aim, kick, push, and you land
in a fencing lunge like this. That's it.
When you land, we want to have both feet
flat on the floor. Uh front foot facing
nice and forwards. Front leg is bent,
back leg straight, and both of your arms
should be straight.
Nice. Pretty good. Ready again. Plunge.
Before our bout started, we needed to
lay some ground rules.
In our match, points would be won by
touching the opponent's electric jacket
with the tip of the foil sword.
Interestingly, this is where the phrase
touche comes from. Anyway, in the rules
of foil fencing, only the fencer with
priority can score a point. How do you
get priority? Either by being the first
to attack or by parrying the opponent's
attack in which the priority is
transferred.
You may then repost by touching the
opponent's jacket after a successful
parry. Got it? Good.
Okay. Before we start fencing, we show
our opponent a lot of respect in
fencing. We do this at the start and at
the end of the match. It's actually
embedded into the rules of the sport. We
do a fencing salute. Full salute. We
point at the floor.
>> Yeah.
>> Bring your guard to your chin. Point at
the ceiling. Nice straight arm. Back to
your chin and back to the floor. Or you
can do the half salute, which is just
chin, point your opponent, and back to
your chin.
>> No salute for you. No respect.
>> No respect.
>> No respect. Even more.
>> Okay. On guard. Are you ready? Fence.
Oh,
>> Luke made a parry, so he blocked and won
the priority. He hit the target, so Luke
scores a point. So, one n to Luke.
>> If you score a point, we go all the way
back to the on guard lines.
>> Are you ready? Fence.
Hold. Luke attacked, but he hit off
target, so no point.
Hold. Okay. Parried, but she hit off
target. So, no. That
>> was a good parry. That was a good parry.
I think
>> just just on the arm as well.
>> Okay.
>> On guard. Are you ready? Yeah. Fence.
>> Oh, Luke attacked. He hit on target.
>> Point for Luke. That's two zero. So,
back to the red lines cuz someone scored
a point.
>> I was beginning to think this was a bit
too easy. Maybe this whole duel business
wasn't so difficult after all.
Oh, Kate attacked. She hit on target.
>> I'm so sorry.
>> In the ball.
>> Point for Kate. So that's 2-1. No, no
double points for that.
>> I'm [laughter] so sorry.
>> Playing dirty.
>> Oh, Luke attacked, but he hit off
target.
>> Clearly, my precision needed work. I was
beginning to feel the pressure,
especially with Kate walking me down.
getting cornered.
>> Oh, attack from Kate. So, you hit on
target, but because Kate was attacking,
she had priority and she hit off target.
So, no point scored. Fence
>> hole. Attack from Kate on target. Point
for Kate. That's two points each. Again,
back behind the red lines.
>> You're going for [music] an interesting
strategy. You're being offensive but
parrying. So, I don't know which what to
do.
>> I don't know what I'm doing. I really
[laughter]
>> with the score tied at 22, it was all
down to the last point. Who would be
declared the dueling master?
>> Attack from Luke on target. Luke wins.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Now at the end again, we have to
return to our starting position.
>> Salute your opponent one more time.
Luke,
>> well done, P.
>> Cool. And at the end of the match, you
shake your opponent's hand with your
nons sword arm. So with the hand without
the glove, give your opponent a nice
>> Okay, that was a really good match.
>> Well done.
>> He likes it. Thank you very much.
>> Oh, it's hot in here, isn't it?
>> I am sweating way more than I expected.
[laughter]
>> Um, I think I had the moral victory. I I
look better in leggings than
>> I also need to go to the gym.
Boyed by my performance, but equally
shattered and concerned about my
extremely shaky legs, I was hoping my
next task would be to sit down, [music]
relax, and write some Latin or analyze a
priceless artifact dating back to
antiquity.
Unfortunately, my tutors had other
ideas. And for my impending lesson,
having leg muscles full of lactic acid
was far from ideal
in the courts of Henry VIII through to
those of James I and other Steuart
monarch.
Dancing and theatrical performances were
all the rage. An integral part of life
in royal palaces, parties in which
noblemen and women would frolic and tap
their feet to the tune of a loot, hoping
to impress the king or queen would be
much anticipated events in the calendar.
Here at Hall Memorial Hall in
Westminster, I was watching a group of
historical dance specialists and
musicians perform as one would at a
mask, a form of festive courtly
entertainment [music] that flourished in
the 16th and early 17th century.
It required fantastic posture, intricate
footwork, timely rhythm, and an aura of
eloquence that took years to perfect.
That's not to mention the beautifully
bright and stylish clothing, which I
would have to dawn if I was to fit in in
the European courts.
Here to guide me through the ritual and
get me up to speed in the art of the
mask during the late TUDA and early
Stewart period is historical dance
specialist Charlotte UT.
>> Well, Charlotte, I certainly uh feel
like a gentleman.
>> Scrub up, don't you? Yeah.
>> Well, speaking of my scrub, can you talk
to me through what I'm wearing? So you
are a sort of classic early James the
first sort of turn of the 17th century
dublet and hose get up here
>> right.
>> Uh so you can see you've got your dublet
here on the top. Uh cloth of silver very
very fashionable. James the first loved
it.
>> Colors are important.
>> Colors are color well colors are
important I think every period but this
you know they of course go out in and
out of fashion but cloth of silver. Look
how wealthy you are. Um you also have of
course your little pawnch here. Sometime
often padded. It's not you, but uh you
know that gives that sort of like noble
peacock,
>> okay,
>> look, you know. So that that's what
>> it's not meant to make you look sort
fatter, which means you're more wealthy.
>> No, it's more to do with again with the
movement of your nobility and your poise
and your stature and that sort of the
peacocking was a thing just called
peacocking. Peacocking.
>> Stick your chest out like a peacock. So
that's that's your uh your d your hose
here. Your big your big baggy trousers.
>> Yeah. Everything's coming back into
fashion now.
>> Yeah. Bag the baggy trout. The baggier
the better.
>> Okay.
>> Uh basically. So the bigger they were, I
mean how much you could afford if you
could afford more material. Um uh but
also it was your huge baggy trousers
that you had uh to show again how how
noble how your high status.
>> It's all about the status. Yeah. You can
afford more more cloth. Therefore
>> big baggy trousers. Yeah. And you've got
garters, cuffs, your collar all pinned
on because of course no no zips, no
poppers. It was all um either pinned uh
with an actual pin or pointed. So they
are, if you can excuse me, but h you can
see here tied with your points here. So
your clothing is literally tied together
uh to hold together something they would
tie their sleeves on often tie your
dublet to your hose
>> by presumably your servant would be
doing.
>> Of course,
>> they must have been spending ages
getting ready. I sometimes think about
that in this sued period.
>> What else are they going to do? There's
no
>> That is very true.
>> No. No TV, no no games.
>> Well, speaking of entertainment,
>> um the you know, in the 17th century
court,
>> Yes.
>> just how important is entertainment?
Because, as you said, there isn't that
much going on? It's all about
flamboyance and showing your wealth.
>> So, it's super important. I mean, it was
your ability to take part in it. And
again, this grew out of the court of
Henry, of Elizabeth. Um the the status
of an amateur wasn't something that you
know we think connotation oh you're not
very good. No to be an amateur was like
to aspire to because you therefore had
the time
>> to practice dancing, playing music, um
fencing, uh doing all of the the sort of
leisure activities you could because you
didn't have to go to work.
>> So you were like, "Oh yeah, I can so I
can practice my art and then aren't I a
good amateur?"
>> Again, it's all about what it
represents, [music] isn't it?
Absolutely.
>> Everything's about representation.
>> Yeah.
>> In the royal courts of the late 16th and
early 17th century, how you dressed and
performed in front of the king or queen
could influence your status within royal
society and hence was taken extremely
seriously.
And as I was about to find out, in one
form of festive entertainment, you
required multiple strings to your bow.
The mask. I've heard this specific form
of entertainment.
>> Yes. A theater. Really?
>> Theater. Okay. What how is that
different to any other forms of
entertainment and dance they would have
been doing?
>> So, well, it was a huge spectacle,
incredibly expensive, incredibly
extravagant, uh, but only for the
aristocracy. Uh, close shop, total close
shop. So, uh, you could only get in if
you're an ambassador, if you're a member
of court, if you're invited,
>> VIP. So, what? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. A bit
like a bit like a big, you know, footsie
100 corporate do only CEOs allowed that
sort of thing, you know, with, you know,
very powerful person, president at the
top or something. So that's that's what
we're going for here. And it was
something that again grew out of just
the courtly entertainments which were
less formal from Henry VII, Elizabeth.
Uh James, he was the one that put it on
the map really in this country. It is a
fusion of singing, dancing, uh spoken
word, and dance being the most
important. Okay. It grew into this big
sort of threesectioned extravaganza of
an anti-mask where you've got sort of
grotesque chaos. All sort some usually a
god or a goddess has caused some sort of
chaotic thing going on. Then you'd have
the noble dancers come on with your big
punchch putting everything to right
solving the chaos in the main mask. And
isn't it good that the king was uh is
there to restore order? It's a political
tool as much as an
>> so it's a narrative. There's a
narrative.
>> Yeah, there is a loose a very loose
narrative when you look at some of them.
They really are quite loose. Um but it's
it's the point is
>> watch this because if we didn't have the
king, we'd have chaos. So we have to
have the king to restore order and the
king is put there by God.
>> So yes and God has appointed the king
and all the nobility to move in the way
that they do. So therefore they can
restore order. Oh, aren't they good?
Aren't we lucky that we've got them? And
then at the end you have a big old party
in the rebels. Uh which is a bit like
doing lots of different dances to
impress the king, but you do them on
your own.
>> And would the king dance?
>> Charles did. So Charles danced as a
prince, a queen, and of Denmark. And
then later Henrietta Mariah, she danced
in the masks. She had her own mask. So
uh it the princesses danced. Uh James,
Duke of York, who was Charles's brother
again, he was renowned as a dancer. So
he danced as well. So you know, it was a
big family business. They would train,
they would go to lessons. Yeah.
>> Charles the first and George Villas when
he was Prince Charles, they had the same
dancing master. So it was like
>> it's all part of becoming the gentleman,
isn't it?
>> Absolutely. Absolutely. as part of their
training how to learn your languages,
learn your dancing, learn your music,
learn your science. You [music] that was
that was that was how you go on a grand
tour, become a gentleman.
With a better understanding of what
would be expected of me in a royal court
of the era, it was time I began my
training, starting off with a few basic
steps.
Now if you are going to [music] be a
true gentleman, if you are going to
aspire to are we aspiring for the very
top here?
>> Very top.
>> Very top then you must learn a galliard.
>> Okay.
>> Yes. A galliard is like the dance that
you do. Now like many of these dances
they became improvisational. Uh but they
had a basic form. Okay. And the basic
form of the galliard it goes to six.
>> Okay. To the beat of six.
>> Yeah. The beat of six or the count of
six. You do I'll have to lift my skirts
up, but you can see my my legs
underneath. You do four kicks forward.
So, one, two, three, four.
>> Okay,
>> off you go.
>> One, two, three, four.
>> Very good. Yes. Now, then on five, you
bring your feet together.
>> Okay.
>> And then on six, you do a little jump in
the air and you twiddle your feet.
>> Oh, that looked a bit awkward, didn't
it?
>> Don't fall flat in your face, mate.
[laughter] That would be bad. Uh, that's
not
>> just a little jump.
>> Just a Well, well, if you're really good
at the galliard,
>> the higher you jump,
>> the higher you jump. There was something
called kicking the tassel. A lady would
hold a tassel and the gentleman with
Galliard and [music] kick it.
>> Would jump as high as you could.
>> Yes. Yes. You could twidd your feet
several times.
>> God, it's going to make you feel like
they get sweaty.
>> Well, they they Well, they're training
for hours and days and weeks to do this.
So, but yes, they would get sweaty, but
they're very fit. So, the whole Galliard
step is four kicks forward. Ready? Okay.
>> And one 2 3 four. Put your feet
together. [music] Five. Jump up. Six.
>> Six. Okay.
>> One. Oh.
>> One. 2 3 4 five.
>> Six. Yeah. Watch your G.
>> Oh, I got it.
>> Yes.
>> Oh dear Luke. Not the best start.
Judging by my jumping ability, a
wardrobe malfunction was the least of my
worries. What's more, making sure your
feet were in rhythm was just the first
step.
>> Once you've got that basic, one, two,
three, four, five, six. You don't just
have to kick forward. Oh, no. You could
kick backwards. You can even kick to the
sides.
>> Oh,
>> yeah.
>> Okay.
>> One, two, three, four, five, six.
>> You'd be dominating the dance floor.
>> That's the whole point. Yeah. [music] It
is, you know, you you've got to show
just how amazing you are at it.
>> Okay. Well, I'll give that a go. So,
we've got the one, two, three, four,
>> five, up, six. Oo, not bad.
>> That was a bit better.
>> I like that little flourishing. You
could turn it.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah,
>> it's a real art form to I mean, we we
laugh about it, but it it takes
training.
>> There's a book from in the period
[music] from Spain which has got 250
different variations in it.
>> 1 2 3 4
>> five six.
>> Would it be both feet or just one?
>> You could. It's It's improvisation.
>> Oh, it's a bit of improvisation.
>> As long as it fits to the count of
[music] six, you can basically do what
you want.
>> If you're caught doing it out of time,
>> mega embarrassment.
>> Well, that means because you can't see
clearly, God isn't running through you
while you're dancing. So, you need to
giving you the gift. Absolutely.
One, two, three, four, five, six.
>> Six.
>> Okay. And then what you do is it's, as I
said, [music] it's a dance off.
>> Yeah.
>> So, one person will come and do four
measures and then another person and
then they go, "Yeah, go on then. You do
it.
>> So, you can do it better."
>> It's similar. It kind of happens today
as well.
>> You see,
>> things don't change. Things don't
change.
>> Yeah. And then if you impress the king,
>> he might give you a castle or something.
>> Wow. So the stakes are high.
>> Stakes are high.
>> And you're kind of trying to one up each
other.
>> So it's not just you've got your
beautiful clothing.
Yeah. Richly decorated and lovely fine
lace and then you walk then you've got
your noble gate
>> and then you've got your amazing dance
ability.
>> Amazing dance. Okay. Well, Charlotte,
shall we have a dance off?
>> Dance off. Right. Come on then.
Okay, Charlotte.
>> Right, we're going to go for it. So,
I'll go first. He's We're going to do
four each.
>> Four each.
>> Four counts of six each. Okay. Then,
Beth, then I'll go and then you will
impress us all.
>> I will.
>> Yes. Immensely on
>> Cue the music.
>> There we go. Thank you, Sam.
Oh, very good. Very good.
>> Got very high.
>> That's you.
>> She's doing it sideways. Sideways. Very
womanike and around.
Off you go.
Sorry.
>> Oh, I'm going. That's probably Oh, can I
start that again? [laughter]
>> 1 2 3
>> Oh, this keeps falling down. Sorry. 1 2
with it around my ankles.
>> [laughter]
>> And with that entertaining performance,
my grand tour came to an abrupt end.
If there was one thing I had learned, it
was that becoming a gentleman in the
16th and 17th century was no easy feat.
Your literal feet were always on the
move. Whether that was in time with the
beat of a loot or to dodge your
opponent's sword in a jewel,
you had to keep both physically and
mentally fit. For it was not just your
dancing ability, horse riding skills, or
weapons handling that would bring you
favor.
It was your ability to express yourself
eloquently and talk about philosophy,
history, art, and architecture.
All in all, it was a right old faf.
Thanks for watching this video on the
life of a gentleman in the TUDA and
Stewart era. And thank you to all the
reenactors, musicians, and dancers, as
well as Fighting Fit Fencing for making
the documentary possible. If you'd like
to learn more about how you'd capture
the heart of a king, join sex historian
Dr. Kate Listister, as she uncovers two
of the most notorious royal favorites of
the 17th century, George Villers and
Nell Gwyn. Royal Favorites is a brand
new two-part exclusive documentary on
History Hit TV. with his stall.